Welcome back, Preppies.
Welcome to our next section of our intermediate speaking course.
In the previous lesson, we learned about the format of the IELTS speaking test.
So what do you need to do to achieve a band 6 in speaking?
To answer this question, today, we're going to learn about the marking
criteria for IELTS speaking test.
To be more specific, we have two main objectives of today's lesson.
Number one, to understand the marking criteria for the IELTS speaking test.
Number two, to understand the difference between band 5 and band 6 in the IELTS speaking.
Accordingly, today's lesson will be divided into two parts, marking criteria
for the IELTS speaking test and the difference between band 5 and band 6 in IELTS speaking.
All right, no more delay.
Let's begin.
To understand the marking criteria for the IELTS speaking test, let's take
a look at the band descriptors published on the IELTS.org website.
Look at this table.
You might notice that there are four main marking criteria for the IELTS speaking test.
They are fluency and coherence, lexical resource, grammatical range and
accuracy, and pronunciation.
Firstly, fluency and coherence focus on factors such as the flow of
speech, the speed, the length of the speech, coherence and cohesion in the speech.
Secondly, lexical resource assesses the candidate's vocabulary, including range
and accuracy of vocabulary used, ability to paraphrase effectively.
Next, grammatical range and accuracy assess candidate's grammar, including the
accuracy of the grammar and the range and variety of grammar structures.
Finally, pronunciation assesses candidate's ability to use accurate
phonological features, a wide range of phonological features.
So now, you have grasped brief information about the four main criteria.
Based on the information I just provided, let's organize the following key indicators into their corresponding criteria.
Key indicators, in other words, are sub-criteria that the examiners use to assess each major criterion.
All right, so here is a summary table of the key indicators
that examiners will use to assess each main marking criterion for the IELTS speaking test.
Well done, guys.
If you completed this exercise correctly, it means you've understood the
characteristics of these four main marking criteria.
Now let me ask you a question.
Among these four criteria, which one is the most important and carries
the highest score in the IELTS speaking test?
Please give your answer through an interactive question below.
Correct answer is E, all of them.
All these four criteria are equally important, with each criterion accounting for 25% of your speaking score.
So it is important for you to improve all four criteria.
Based on this information, if a candidate has the following scores for
the four criteria, what would be her or his speaking score be?
The average score of four criteria is 5.25. However, unfortunately, the
score is rounded down to five, instead of being rounded up to 5.5.
Unlike the overall score for four skills, when the sub -score for each skill will be rounded down.
Until now, you've gained a basic understanding of four marking criteria in the IELTS speaking test, right?
However, to identify your weaknesses and specific plans for improving your
speaking skills, you need to understand the difference between the criteria for band five and band six.
Therefore, let's move on to part two, the difference between band five and band six in IELTS speaking.
In this part, we'll learn more about the differences between five and six in each criterion.
This will help you know which parts you need to focus on to improve.
Let's start by looking at the fluency and coherence criterion for band five and band six.
Here are some smaller criteria for the fluency coherence criterion in five and six bands.
Now, I have a challenge for you.
On the screen, there are two sample answers of the two candidates in the IELTS speaking test.
Please decide which statement belongs to band five, which one is in
band six, and put them into two columns below, based on three factors.
The ability to keep going with the answer, hesitations, and the use of discourse markers.
You have one minute to do this task.
Three, two, one, go.
Time's up.
Everyone, here's my answer.
And these are also the differences between the sub criteria of the
fluency and coherence criterion in band five and six.
Now, let's explore the differences between band five and six in the lexical resource criterion.
Here are some sub criteria for lexical resource in these two bands.
Based on the two sample answers, you have 30 seconds to decide
which criteria belong to band five and which criteria belong to band six.
Finished?
Let's check the answer together.
First, I will compare sentence one and sentence three, because both sentences
have the same words, resource sufficient, which means how the two candidates use different words.
When comparing the range of vocabulary in the band five and band
six sample answers, we can see that candidates at band six use
a broader range of vocabulary related to work and leisure, such as
overwork, leisure possibilities, entertainment options, and challenging working schedule.
Although some words may not be suitable, but overall, the candidate conveyed
the meaning of the answer very effectively.
On the other hand, the candidate at band five only used basic
words like work hard, play, and hobby, which limited their answer.
Moreover, band six used phrases at higher levels as collocations, find it
difficult, spend time on, and lead to.
Therefore, sentence one belongs to band six and sentence three belongs to band five.
The remaining two sentences contain the keyword paraphrase, which refers to the
ability to paraphrase in these two band scores.
Now let's look at the band five sample.
We can see that even though the candidate tried to paraphrase the
phrase less leisure time, it wasn't paraphrased accurately.
So sentence four belongs to band five.
On the other hand, in the band six, the candidate paraphrased it correctly.
So sentence two belongs to band six.
Now let's take a look at the differences in the lexical resource
criterion between band five and band six.
Now let's move on to the grammatical range and accuracy criterion of the band five and band six.
Let's take a look at the sub criteria of these two bands.
In one minute, based on the two sample answers decide which criteria
belong to band five and which criteria belong to band six.
Have you finished?
Let's check the answer together.
We can see that sentence one mentions different types of sentences like
short sentences, complex sentences, and a variety of structures.
While sentence three mentions basic sentence forms, this means that these two
sentences assess the grammar range.
In the band five, we mostly see simple sentences.
However, when it comes to using complex sentences, there are still some errors.
For example, using when before on a Sunday or using both because and so together.
In band six, we can see that the candidate used a wider range of grammar.
For example, he or she used a complex sentence with relative clauses or flexibility used linking words.
So sentence three belongs to band five and sentence one belongs to band six.
Sentences two and four have the word errors.
This means that these two sentences assess the grammar accuracy.
We can see that the candidate in band five has more errors
when using complex sentences compared to the candidate in band six.
Also, the candidate in band five use less complex sentences compared to band six candidate.
So sentence four belongs to band five and sentence two belongs to band six.
So these are sub criteria of grammatical range and accuracy for band five and six.
Now let's move on to the final criterion, which is pronunciation.
For this criterion, I will provide a comparison table of the sub
criteria for band five and band six.
Basically, in band six, some individual words are mispronounced, but this only
causes occasional lack of clarity.
Besides, the candidate can use some advanced phonological features such as
intonation, sentence stress, linking sounds, but it is still limited.
Chunking is appropriate, but may be affected by a lack of stress timing and or a rapid speech rate.
This means that not stressing syllables appropriately can affect the flow and
rhythm of the candidate's speech or speaking too fast can also affect
the overall rhythm and clarity of the speech.
In general, the examiner can still understand the speech without much effort.
Meanwhile, we do not have a detailed description for band five.
Band descriptors only mention displays all the positive features of band four
and some but not all of the positive features of band six.
So how do you bridge the gap from band five to band six?
Here is your four-step game plan.
First, for fluency, stop worrying about hesitation.
Focus on structure.
Don't just give a short answer.
Expand it using the ARE method.
Answer, reason, example.
Second, for vocabulary, stop memorizing lists of single words.
Focus on collocations, words that naturally go together.
This shows the examiner you understand how English is actually used.
Third, for grammar, you need variety.
Don't play it safe with only simple sentences.
Push yourself to use complex structures like conditional IF sentences or relative clauses.
Mistakes are okay.
Being too simple is not.
And finally, for pronunciation, focus on chunking.
Don't speak like a robot word by word.
Group your words together into natural phrases to create a smooth rhythm.
If you practice these four strategies daily, it won't be long before you see your score improve.
All right.
Today, we've learned about four marking criteria in IELTS speaking.
What are those four criteria?
Let's choose the correct answers.